<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[MHC1 Garden]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/</link><image><url>https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>MHC1 Garden</title><link>https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/</link></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 04:52:21 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 04:52:20 GMT</pubDate><copyright><![CDATA[George Shoemaker]]></copyright><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator>George Shoemaker</dc:creator><item><title><![CDATA[ 2mi Results]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1VzQX3GlrOscF7hUgj_C7QNWKZCg79wrEWXLWwQ3uHbo/edit?usp=sharing" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1VzQX3GlrOscF7hUgj_C7QNWKZCg79wrEWXLWwQ3uHbo/edit?usp=sharing" target="_blank"><strong></strong></a>Results Google Sheet (ask me for access)<br><br>UPDATE: 4 more individuals did the assessment on 03JAN. The goal is to create A/B/C training groups. For missing members I made a best guess for which group they fit into.<br>14 participants, still missing a few crewmembers<br>I believe the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="2mi-plan" data-href="2mi-plan" href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/crew-pt/2-mile-time-trial/2mi-plan.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">course</a> is 10 seconds slower than on a track (elevation + hard turn around).<br>
<br>Observations

<br>Group's average time was ~17 minutes
<br>All but one person overestimated their performance
<br>Average "best guess" overestimated performance by 10% 


]]></description><link>https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/crew-pt/2-mile-time-trial/2mi-results.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">crew-pt/2-mile-time-trial/2mi-results.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[George Shoemaker]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 04:20:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[2mi Plan]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The 2 mile time trial is an Aerobic Fitness assessment. Participants should run the course at max effort. The goal of facilitators is to accurately record times.<br><br>
<br>Start / Finish

<br>37.350556, -121.909611
<br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/w3Mhe8jBNwVWkPZc8" target="_blank">https://maps.app.goo.gl/w3Mhe8jBNwVWkPZc8</a>


<br>Turn Around Point

<br>37.363177, -121.918540
<br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/x1tttuhTQDGpJkVA9" target="_blank">https://maps.app.goo.gl/x1tttuhTQDGpJkVA9</a>


<br>Hazards

<br>Missing the turn around

<br>If you reach Skyport Dr overpass (overpass #2), you've gone too far.


<br>Unpaved sections

<br>Uneven dirt, rocks, mud, puddles


<br>Members of public, homeless


<br><img alt="two-mile-tt.png" src="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/lib/media/two-mile-tt.png"><br><br>
<br>Time keeper at Start / Finish

<br>Needs a clipboard / pen / <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1VzQX3GlrOscF7hUgj_C7QNWKZCg79wrEWXLWwQ3uHbo/edit?usp=sharing" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1VzQX3GlrOscF7hUgj_C7QNWKZCg79wrEWXLWwQ3uHbo/edit?usp=sharing" target="_blank">blank results sheet</a>(ask me for file permission).
<br>Stopwatch


<br>Turn around person or clearly mark Turn Around (flagging tape + signage)
<br><br>
<br>Jog from station to <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://maps.app.goo.gl/w3Mhe8jBNwVWkPZc8" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/w3Mhe8jBNwVWkPZc8" target="_blank">Start / Finish</a>
<br>Explain this an out &amp; back, how to identify the turn around point
<br>5 minutes to prepare, turn around person leaves to get in position
<br>Mass start, begin timer
<br>Crewmembers run to turn around point and return
<br>Time keeper records times as crewmembers finish
<br>Return to station
]]></description><link>https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/crew-pt/2-mile-time-trial/2mi-plan.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">crew-pt/2-mile-time-trial/2mi-plan.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[George Shoemaker]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 04:25:05 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/lib/media/two-mile-tt.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/lib/media/two-mile-tt.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Crew PT]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br><a data-href="pt-log" href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/crew-pt/pt-log.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">pt-log</a>
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="mhc1-pt-proposal" data-href="mhc1-pt-proposal" href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/crew-pt/mhc1-pt-proposal.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">mhc1-pt-proposal</a>

<br>How I think we should plan crew PT
<br>Presented to leadership late DEC2024


<br><a data-href="2mi-plan" href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/crew-pt/2-mile-time-trial/2mi-plan.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">2mi-plan</a>
<br><br>
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.tacticalbarbell.com/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.tacticalbarbell.com/" target="_blank">Tactical Barbell</a> collection of books by K. Black

<br>Disclaimer: PDFs are for educational purposes. <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.amazon.com/stores/K-Black/author/B00LJC25PG?ref=ap_rdr&amp;isDramIntegrated=true&amp;shoppingPortalEnabled=true" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.amazon.com/stores/K-Black/author/B00LJC25PG?ref=ap_rdr&amp;isDramIntegrated=true&amp;shoppingPortalEnabled=true" target="_blank">Buy the books</a> if you like them.
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://tacticalbarbell.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=1485" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://tacticalbarbell.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=1485" target="_blank">WHERE DO I START? forum post</a>
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1aT53c_WcJmRCyCLWwoAhDVjSGyQxDmAd/view?usp=sharing" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1aT53c_WcJmRCyCLWwoAhDVjSGyQxDmAd/view?usp=sharing" target="_blank">TB I: Strength PDF</a>

<br>Most relevant to me because I want to get stronger


<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1--hg83jEbSsPFsleU-O3qt36PboGegvd/view?usp=sharing" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1--hg83jEbSsPFsleU-O3qt36PboGegvd/view?usp=sharing" target="_blank">TB II: Conditioning PDF</a>

<br>Confusingly this is not a sequel to TB I, it's a stand alone book.
<br>Have yet to read it as of JAN2025


<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1YvRMu2-2Mpd7OzPxFG2z5s8KAym98nyk/view?usp=sha" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1YvRMu2-2Mpd7OzPxFG2z5s8KAym98nyk/view?usp=sha" target="_blank">TB Green Protocol PDF</a>, endurance specialty book

<br>Most relevant to Wildland Firefighting in general




<br>Run For Your Life, Mark Cucuzzella, M.D.

<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.hoopladigital.com/ebook/run-for-your-life-mark-cucuzzella/12766117" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.hoopladigital.com/ebook/run-for-your-life-mark-cucuzzella/12766117" target="_blank">Available on Hoopla</a> free with your public library card
<br>Author is a doctor, researcher, marathoner, ex Air Force
<br>Running technique, energy system physiology, training methods


<br><br>
Attributes or fitness domains are things like maximal-strength, speed, strength-endurance or aerobic capacity.  Tools are things like bench press, sandbags, kettlebells, hills, and your bodyweight. For the operational athlete, training is about improving the attribute, not about getting better at using the tool.
<br>
There’s block periodization wherein you focus on mostly one fitness domain at a time before moving on to the next. For example, block 1 would be several weeks focused on aerobic base building, block two might be maximal-strength and work capacity, and block 3 could be sport specific drills.
<br>
Periodization can also refer to how you manipulate frequency/volume and<br>
progression within the context of strength training. [eg <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Progressive_overload" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Progressive_overload" target="_blank">Progressive Overload</a>]
<br>
Periodization gives you a plan. Before you set foot in the gym, you’ll know what exercises to perform, number of sets, number of reps and load.
]]></description><link>https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/crew-pt/crew-pt.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">crew-pt/crew-pt.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[George Shoemaker]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 04:32:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[MHC1 Physical Training Proposal]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>SPC Shoemaker in collaboration with SPC Hammack<br>
v20241231<br>In this plan I present an actionable guide to PT programming for the crew that aligns with well known principals of physical training to make us stronger, faster, and more durable. At minimum we should run 3 workouts per week that respectively target Max Strength, Aerobic Fitness, and Work Capacity. For Strength &amp; Aerobic Fitness the crew should be divided into training groups based on measured ability for that particular domain.<br><br>
<br>The minimum allotted time for crew PT is 3h / week per Lt. Col. Riley.
<br>The pairing of training stimulus followed by sufficient recovery yields physical improvement.
<br>Progressive Overload training is how to developing Maximum Strength efficiently.
<br>Endurance training at Aerobic Threshold effort is optimal for developing Aerobic Fitness.
<br>Max Strength and Aerobic Fitness are the foundation of exceptional Work Capacity.<a data-footref="1" href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/about:blank#fn-1-fc1c977953062bd2" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[1]</a>
<br>All workouts must explicitly target one of the following domains of fitness:

<br>Maximum Strength
<br>Aerobic Fitness
<br>Work Capacity


<br>While training will sometimes be uncomfortable to achieve a sufficient stimulus, no single workout should break off a crew member. When we PT in the morning we must keep fire ready for the day. Excessive fatigue, vomiting, and pushing through acute pain are to be avoided. Such max efforts must be reserved for infrequent tests (Type Out), competitions (Stand Down), or an exceptional situation in the field where an absolute max effort is justified by the danger of the situation.  <br><br>
<br>Progressive Overload: In strength training, this is the principal of adding more resistance over time in order to stimulate continued adaption and build strength efficiently.
<br>Aerobic Fitness: The body's ability to effectively supply oxygen to muscles during sustained exercise such as hiking, cutting line, running at a steady pace, etc. Also responsible for resetting the anaerobic energy system after a short explosive effort.
<br>Anaerobic Fitness: The body's ability to deliver short bursts of energy in the absence of oxygen. Examples include sprinting, HIIT, or moving heavy objects explosively.
<br>Aerobic Threshold: A sustained effort just above the "optimal endurance training zone" and below an anaerobic effort.<a data-footref="2" href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/about:blank#fn-2-fc1c977953062bd2" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[2]</a> A rule of thumb is to run at the limit of nasal breathing. This idea is similar to "Zone 2" or Long Steady State training.

<br><img alt="cucuzella-zones.png" src="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/lib/media/cucuzella-zones.png">


<br>Work capacity: "[T]he ability to recover quickly and use multiple muscle groups requiring your cardiovascular, musculoskeletal and central nervous system to work together efficiently".<a data-footref="3" href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/about:blank#fn-3-fc1c977953062bd2" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[3]</a> This is critical for Wildland Firefighters who must perform dynamic physical tasks for prolonged periods.
<br>Stimulus-Fatigue-Recovery-Adaptation (SFRA) Theory: The key idea is that fatigue induced by a training stimulus decreases apparent performance in the short term. Only with adequate rest is an increase in physical ability (Supercompensation) achieved.<a data-footref="4" href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/about:blank#fn-4-fc1c977953062bd2" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[4]</a> Adaptation does not require total rest, however. You can target different stimulus day to day. One total rest day / week is advisable.

<br><img alt="sfra-curve.png" src="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/lib/media/sfra-curve.png">


<br><br>Given that we are allotted 3h / week minimum for crew PT, it makes sense to run a workout on Monday / Wednesday / Friday. The three workouts are purposefully very different to provide specific stimulus for Strength, Aerobic Fitness and Work capacity respectively:<br>Monday: Max Strength Specific lifting sessions will be designed by SPC Hammack and follow a cycle targeting Push, Pull, or Leg movements each week. Workouts will consist of 3 movements for 3-5 sets of 5-12 reps to optimize for Max Strength. Sufficient rest between sets to reset the body and maintain form is critical. For heavy dynamic movements, weight is assigned as a percentage of estimated 1 Repetition Maximum and should gradually increase overtime (Progressive Overload).<br>Wednesday: Aerobic Fitness Primarily organized by SPC Shoemaker, and typically a run at Aerobic Threshold effort. This is a high tempo, yet sustainable pace. Runs beyond 30 minutes are ideal stimulus and should be executed with near even splits. Overtime we expect to see more speed / distance at the same intensity (Aerobic Adaptation). Alternatively we can do a hike, ERG row, stationary bike, or continuous basketball day.<br>Friday: Work Capacity This is where we combine Max Strength &amp; Aerobic Fitness for an up-tempo workout that bleeds into Anaerobic effort. This can be circuit training, HIIT, Every Minute on the Minute, or an Indian Run. It is the least structured workout and is meant to be a group challenge that simulates the dynamic work we must do on the fire line.<br> The most fit members of the crew can easily incorporate the M/W/F workouts into their programming. For the crew member that does no PT beyond what is prescribed, we expect to still see improvement via "beginner gains". SPC Hammack's Push / Pull / Leg specific workouts will allow less experienced lifters to learn new lifts do their own strength sessions. Likewise runs prescribed at Aerobic Threshold pace will give lesser runners a reprieve from crew runs that are too fast, while still giving them ideal stimulus to improve.<br><br>When organizing a PT session, it is simplest to assign the same workout to everyone. Given the variance in ability among the crew, this strategy violates Principal #6: All workouts must explicitly target either Strength, Aerobic Fitness, or Work Capacity. Why is this?<br>Let's say the crew is assigned a 4 mile run at 9'30" / mi pace. For the most capable runner on the crew, this pace is well below their Aerobic Threshold pace of 7'45" / mi. For the worst runner they will quickly exceed their aerobic limit and fall off the pace, despite giving their max effort. Both are receiving a sub-optimal stimulus in opposite directions. And for the crew member who went anaerobic, the stimulus is unproductive: The "toxic, acidic environment in the muscles [from high-intensity workouts] inhibit the aerobic development we seek."<a data-footref="5" href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/about:blank#fn-5-fc1c977953062bd2" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[5]</a><br>You can imagine a similar scenario for a strength workout with free weights: The strongest crew member can easily squat a barbell loaded with 250 lbs whereas an inexperienced lifter will risk injury by handling such weight. It's unproductive.<br>The worst possible result of overwhelming stimulus is over training or injury. This happens when the Stimulus-Fatigue (of SFRA Theory) compounds in the abscence of Recovery-Adaption such that P (Performance) degrades in the long term. We can avoid this.<br><br>A straight forward solution to the above problems is to create workout-specific "teams" based on measured ability.<br>Let's reframe the 4 mile crew run from above: We want the crew to run approximately 40 minutes at a pace that is close to their Aerobic Threshold. Let's split thew crew into Alpha, Bravo &amp; Charlie groups. Alpha will run at 8' / mi for 5 miles. Bravo will run at 9'30" / mi for 4 miles. Charlie will run at 11' / mi for 3.5 miles. The variance in distance / pace of each group allows us to roughly normalize the 40 minutes of aerobic training stimulus for everyone.<br>We can determine the running teams by collecting 2 mi time trial results. We can then calculate and assign Aerobic Threshold paces and test if they are appropriate with feedback and GPS tracking.<br>Similarly for strength sessions, we can assign A/B/C groups based on measured 1 Rep Max for dynamic lifts. Taking a percentage of that result allows us to determine the team's training weight for a given movement. We can employ Progressive Overload by increasing that percentage over time.<br>To ensure the training groups are split correctly and that assigned workouts are effective, we will need to constantly receive feedback and adjust. Maybe the training weight was too easy for an individual, and they should move up a group. Maybe the group as a whole has improved, and they are ready for a modest increase in weight. Within a group stronger individuals can bump up the reps so long as they are capable of completing all the assigned sets.<br>While the Strength and Aerobic Fitness sessions should be split into teams, I envision the Work Capacity workouts to be done together as a crew, doubling as a teamwork and morale building exercise.<br><br>For much of the crew the M/W/F programming is not enough to continue progressing. The frequency of stimulus isn't there so additional runs and lifts throughout the week would flesh out the training. To help people focus their efforts we can ask what their individual fitness goals are and check in with them periodically. Example goals could be to bench press one's body weight for 1 rep, run the 2 mile in 14 minutes, or do 1 rep of 1.5x bodyweight for the Back Squat, etc..<br>By hitting the three major workouts weekly, tailoring stimulus via workout teams, and promoting a culture of regular and purposeful training, we can become a more competitive, durable, and capable crew.<br><br>
<br>Start the M/W/F workout cycle.
<br>Create groups and plan workouts with available info.
<br>Execute the 1 Rep Max Day &amp; 2 Mile Test Day to calculate training figures.
<br>Continuously monitor and adjust programming based on individual and team progress / feedback.
<br>Collect personal fitness goals. Periodically monitor progress.
<br>Repeat the 1 Rep Max Day and 2 Mile Test Day every 3 months.
<br>1 Rep Max Day  <br>
<br>Goal: Test individuals' 1 Rep Max as input for A/B/C training teams and computed training weight.
<br>Training weight calculation:

<br>Take the 1 rep and multiply it by some percentage in the range of 50-80%.
<br>For example a 1 Rep Max of 220lbs at 70% yields a training weight of ~150lbs.
<br>The percentage will increase over time as the team adapts (Progressive Overload).


<br>Procedure

<br>Warm up specific to the movement
<br>Coaching on the movement
<br>Break out into groups to test 1 Rep Max for:

<br>Bench Press
<br>Back Squat
<br>(Hex Bar) Dead Lift 




<br>2 Mile Test Day  <br>
<br>Goal: Measure relative running ability as input for A/B/C training teams and computed Aerobic Threshold training pace.
<br>Aerobic Threshold training pace calculation:

<br>Plug the 2 mile time into the Luke Humphrey Running Pace Calculator<a data-footref="6" href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/about:blank#fn-6-fc1c977953062bd2" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[6]</a> and record the faster limit of the "Moderate" pace output.
<br>For example a 14 minute 2 mile will yield a "Moderate" pace output of 9'10" / mi pace for the faster limit.


<br>Procedure

<br>1 mile warm up and dynamic stretches
<br>Set up timers and course (ideally at a track)
<br>Run 2 mi at max effort
<br>Record times
<br>Cool down


<br><br>Max Strength: Push Day<br>
<br>Warm up
<br>Emphasize rest between reps for quality sets, 2-3 minutes minimum
<br>Break out into A/B/C teams &amp; cycle through the following exercises:

<br>4x 6-8 Barbell Bench Press
<br>5x 8-12 Tricep push downs
<br>4x 6-8 seated shoulder press


<br>Aerobic Fitness: ~40 minute Aerobic Threshold Run   <br>
<br>Dynamic warm up
<br>Emphasize even pacing, stick with your team
<br>Break out into teams:

<br>Alpha: Run at 8' / mi for 5 miles
<br>Bravo: Run at  9'30" / mi for 4 miles
<br>Charlie: Run at 11'00 / mi for 3.5 miles


<br>Group stretch
<br>Work Capacity: Every Minute On the Minute (EMOM)  <br>
<br>Warm up
<br>EMOM for 20 minutes. For each minute do:

<br>Basketball court out and back sprint
<br>Alternate between push &amp; pull

<br>Push: 10x Push Up
<br>Pull: 3x Pull Up or 5x Barbell Row




<br>Group stretch
<br><br><br><br><br><br><br>
<br>
<br>"Work Capacity Test" Brochure, United States Forest Service <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.fs.usda.gov/sites/default/files/2023-03/Work-Capacity-Test-brochure.pdf" target="_blank">https://www.fs.usda.gov/sites/default/files/2023-03/Work-Capacity-Test-brochure.pdf</a><a href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/about:blank#fnref-1-fc1c977953062bd2" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Run For Your Life: How to Run, Walk, and Move Without Pain or Injury, Mark Cucuzzella, Chapter 7<a href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/about:blank#fnref-2-fc1c977953062bd2" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>"What Is Your Work Capacity?", Stew Smith, Military.com, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.military.com/military-fitness/general-fitness/what-is-your-work-capacity" target="_blank">https://www.military.com/military-fitness/general-fitness/what-is-your-work-capacity</a><a href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/about:blank#fnref-3-fc1c977953062bd2" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>"The Science and Practice of Periodization: A Brief Review", Anthony Turner, London Sport Institute, Middlesex University, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="http://instituteofmotion.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/The_Science_and_Practice_of_Periodization.pdf" target="_blank">http://instituteofmotion.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/The_Science_and_Practice_of_Periodization.pdf</a><a href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/about:blank#fnref-4-fc1c977953062bd2" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Run For Your Life: How to Run, Walk, and Move Without Pain or Injury, Mark Cucuzzella, Chapter 7<a href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/about:blank#fnref-5-fc1c977953062bd2" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
<br>Luke Humphrey Running Pace Calculator, <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://lukehumphreyrunning.com/hmmcalculator/race_equivalency_calculator.php" target="_blank">https://lukehumphreyrunning.com/hmmcalculator/race_equivalency_calculator.php</a><a href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/about:blank#fnref-6-fc1c977953062bd2" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
]]></description><link>https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/crew-pt/mhc1-pt-proposal.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">crew-pt/mhc1-pt-proposal.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[George Shoemaker]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 04:32:35 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/lib/media/cucuzella-zones.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/lib/media/cucuzella-zones.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[PT Log]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Completed PT is documented here<br><br>Work Capacity stimulus<br>
<br>15 cycles of

<br>bb court run
<br>alternating 5x hanging leg lift / 10x kb swing


<br>materials

<br>2x pull up bar
<br>30-40lb kb &amp; dumbells
<br>(speaker)


<br>Morning was time constrained. EMOM set up / break down is quick. Hammack’s EMOM music track is helpful. Crew enjoys the workout, high tempo but attainable for everyone.<br><br>Max Strength assessment<br>Hammack's self assessment:<br><br>
<br>First formation dismissal: gave time to prep gym
<br>Technique instruction and how to safely fail a lift: Gave people confidence to try their best while avoiding injury
<br>Non-formal "coaching" approach: Allowed Hammack to engage with crew in an approachable, encouraging way. Environment is non judgemental and safe for everyone.
<br>Shoemaker acting as scribe: Allowed Hammack to give people attention as needed.
<br><br>   • Elaborate on the the importance of rest between warm ups / sets / 1 rep max attempts<br>
<br>Better crowd control: Some time spent in "bro session" mode, Bravo entered the gym and side tracked Alpha.
<br>A more in depth class on technique prior to the session: Would cut down the time to complete the assessment
<br><br>Aerobic Fitness assessment<br><a data-href="2mi-results" href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/crew-pt/2-mile-time-trial/2mi-results.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">2mi-results</a><br>I estimate the course is 10 sec slower than a track (slope, hard turn around). Placed pink flagging at turn around.<br>Before the assessment I asked people their “best guess” for a 2 mile time for two reasons:<br>
<br>Hammack thought self-reported times would overestimate performance. This was largely correct - average guess was 10% faster than recorded time.
<br>My hope was that by stating a goal time, people would take the assessment more seriously and try to hit that time.
]]></description><link>https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/crew-pt/pt-log.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">crew-pt/pt-log.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[George Shoemaker]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 04:48:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Bull Run]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://maps.app.goo.gl/xkbUmKuCJvsoD8fY6?g_st=com.google.maps.preview.copy" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/xkbUmKuCJvsoD8fY6?g_st=com.google.maps.preview.copy" target="_blank">Primary Location</a><br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.weather.gov/wrh/fire?wfo=mtr&amp;LAT=37.5800&amp;LON=-121.8438" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.weather.gov/wrh/fire?wfo=mtr&amp;LAT=37.5800&amp;LON=-121.8438" target="_blank">Fire Weather</a>]]></description><link>https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/projects/bull-run.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">projects/bull-run.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[George Shoemaker]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 04:24:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Oakland]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>aka Joaquin Miller Park<br>Entrance: <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://maps.app.goo.gl/o28YMC7kuxLPA3uX6?g_st=com.google.maps.preview.copy" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/o28YMC7kuxLPA3uX6?g_st=com.google.maps.preview.copy" target="_blank">3600 Joaquin Miller Rd, Oakland, CA 94602</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.weather.gov/wrh/fire?wfo=mtr&amp;LAT=37.5800&amp;LON=-121.8438" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.weather.gov/wrh/fire?wfo=mtr&amp;LAT=37.5800&amp;LON=-121.8438" target="_blank">Fire Weather</a>]]></description><link>https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/projects/oakland.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">projects/oakland.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[George Shoemaker]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 04:22:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Home Page]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Target audience is members of MHC1 🤝<br><br>This website is maintained by George Shoemaker. This is not a blog nor a repository of documents. This website is a <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://maggieappleton.com/garden-history/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://maggieappleton.com/garden-history/" target="_blank">Digital Garden</a>  – a living digital notebook where I can easily record and edit information online.<br><br>
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="crew-pt" data-href="crew-pt" href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/crew-pt/crew-pt.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Crew PT</a>
<br>Projects

<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="bull-run" data-href="bull-run" href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/projects/bull-run.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Bull Run Project</a>
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="oakland" data-href="oakland" href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/projects/oakland.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Oakland Project</a>


<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="site-issues" data-href="site-issues" href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/site-issues.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Site Issues</a>
<br><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="mhc1-pt-proposal" data-href="mhc1-pt-proposal" href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/crew-pt/mhc1-pt-proposal.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">MHC1 Physical Training Proposal</a><br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="pt-log" data-href="pt-log" href="https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/crew-pt/pt-log.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">PT Log</a><br><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.nwcg.gov/committee/6-minutes-for-safety" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.nwcg.gov/committee/6-minutes-for-safety" target="_blank">6 Minutes For Safety</a>]]></description><link>https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">index.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[George Shoemaker]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 04:52:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Site Issues]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>
<br>Some nested lists don't render properly
<br>Home Page is labelled as "index"
<br>TODO: Clean up git history
<br>Switch to <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://github.com/KosmosisDire/obsidian-webpage-export" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://github.com/KosmosisDire/obsidian-webpage-export" target="_blank">Export to HTML</a> plug in
<br>Nested indentation renders with newline for some reason

<br>For example


]]></description><link>https://george-a-shoemaker.github.io/mhc1/site-issues.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">site-issues.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[George Shoemaker]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 04:51:17 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>